[Music]
hey hey welcome back it's day three
starting to kind of get a rhythm which
is fun I think we've got a really good
app for you today as well I wanted to
first introduce my my crew that was with
me yesterday I forgot but they are
they're still here so we got Keegan age
eight mommy and Bowen and working
together and then we've also got
McKinley but you guys want to say good
morning good morning you guys work this in the
morning right alright so let's go ahead
and show you what we're up to today
so today's mission so we are building a
game called amazing game that's a pun
alright
amazing game is what we're after today
and what we've got today is that you're
going to get some custom images from the
internet that's what we're going to
start with today to where you have a
hero so my hero in this case is the
pigeon a target that they're trying to
get to so I'm trying to get to the
hotdog and then also a villain and so my
villain in this case is the duckling
he's a sneaky duckling but your goal is
to get around the maze so you're gonna
have to draw the maze get to the hot dog
or whatever your target is to try to win
now I'm showing you this with with my
characters the pigeon the duckling and
the hot dog and so there he loses so he
has to go back to the start but what
you're going to do is you're going to
come up with your own things um in fact
you can probably do this first like
before we even get started today so like
with your adult think about three images
so you can either hero in this case it's
my pigeon you need the target that your
hero is trying to get to and then you
need some villain that's gonna be like
zooming around the screen trying to do
things so hopefully with a little bit of
adult supervision open up Google and
decide what you want to search for so
I'm gonna make mine today with a
different theme just because it can be
whatever theme you want right and so I'm
gonna make mine with kind of like a
veggie tales theme you can tell what we
watch
around town we did the mo Williams
example there we watched Mo
Williams on YouTube and then VeggieTales
so the way you find a good image is
you put in the thing you want to find so
I want to find Larryboy from
VeggieTales
now just searching the internet maybe
you'll find a good image but
perhaps not so you want to filter those
results by clicking on the word images
in Google now I've got a lot of images I
can do one better though I want an image
with a transparent background because I
don't want rectangles going around my
screen so what I'm going to do is I'm
gonna click on tools and then color
transparent now what this is going to do
whoops what this is going to do is this
is going to filter those results for
ones with transparent backgrounds so I'm
gonna find one that I like maybe I like
this one right here the best and click
on it and then I need to save this to my
computer so I'm just gonna right click
and say save image as and you can see
that I've actually prepared this in
advance so I chose to save three images
I chose to save a LarryBoy a bob and a
Moetato change the file names
because they always come down as crazy
file names to where it's a nice simple
name then that way when you import it
into Tynker you'll be all set so pause
the video and get yourself three images
a hero a villain and a target which I've
already done and then once you've got
those saved to your computer then come
back so pause it and go do that
everybody got their images alright
so now everybody's got their images
now let's bring them into Tynker so I
guess what I need to do first is I need
to go create a new project so create a
new project you can click on blank
project that works fine but I always
like to click on blank block coding
project I'm 99.99% sure they're the same
but I still click on blank block coding
project now inside of here I've
currently got my monster I don't need my
monster so I'm just going to delete him
so I clicked on the little three dots
and delete and so now he's gone now what
I want to do is I want to add my actors
one at a time so I'm gonna click on add
actor I'm gonna click on upload actor
and I'm gonna go find where on my
computer I saved them
probably it's easiest just to put them
right into your downloads folder so here
I'm gonna bring in Larry boy when you
bring in an image they may come in like
jumbo right so my larry boy came in huge
just grab the handles and shrink them
down to a good size Larry Boy is gonna
be walking through the maze and so just
like the ship yesterday if I make him
just kind of small that I can make a
more complex maze right next up I want
to upload I'll do my target so Larry boy
is trying to get to Bob I thought about
trying to to bring in Bob and then I
could kind of like put him in jail maybe
or something like that I don't know
maybe I'll do that as a feature but he's
trying to get to Bob you can start your
hero wherever you like but usually I
like to do some corner right so I'll do
the lower left corner of where he's
starting and then my target I don't know
I'll move him around later and then I
also need my villain so I'm gonna say
upload actor and I'm gonna bring in my
villain who if you happen to know
VeggieTales is moetato and I kind of
like for my villain to be a little
bigger and makes them scary right and so
that is what you need to do to kind of
get yourself set up and you need to size
your images just to give you
some ideas I'm gonna see what the
family has decided to do so Keegan
what what is your theme today minions he
likes minions so who's your hero your
villain and your target okay and he's
trying to get to the party Bowen what's
your theme today cool they're all geckos
you've got a good gecko theme going evil
gecko he looked really evil and McKinley
what's your theme so we've got a horse
yeah
avoid the mountain lion that's a
good plan alright so you guys have your
images you brought them into tynker and
we're ready to start doing some stuff
with them that sounds great
alright alright so let's dive in and get
started first I'm gonna make my stage
just a little smaller just so I've got a
little more screen real estate I also
want to save my game so you can title
yours whatever you'd like
I call this amazing game because it's a
pun and I like puns I could go ahead and
publish it now but I'm not going to but
this is connecting with code 2020 day 3
so I'll just hit save for now and then
later I'll publish it alright so we've
got to decide where we want to start we
could start by drawing some of the the
grid like maze oh I forgot to mention on
that grid like maze if you try to walk
through the walls it doesn't let you
right so you can't walk through the
walls so we have to add code to actually
enforce not going through walls so we
could draw the maze first we could do
our hero walking around first it doesn't
really matter
I like code so let's start with code so
find your hero so the hero for me is
Larry Boy and I'm gonna click on Larry
Boy and I can see that I'm gonna start
editing his code because I've got my
little icon in here so what I want to do
with Larry Boy is we will have an on
start in a minute but instead we're
gonna move him with arrows so I'm gonna
bring over when up arrow pressed and
let's go and add some code to it and
then we'll duplicate it because we're
gonna do it like 4 times right so after
we press the up arrow we want some
motion to happen the motion that we want
to happen is we want Larry boy or
whoever our hero is to move up 10 pixels
there's a couple ways we could do that
one way is we can do this like change Y
by 10 pixels but we're gonna do it
different we're gonna point in that
direction so we need point in Direction
90 degrees and the reason we're pointing
by the way this is just kind of a
spoiler alert is because whenever we hit a
wall we want to go the opposite
direction so keeping track of which way
pointing is going to help us keep track
of which way we bounce backwards right
so we're going to point in that
direction
now right now it says point in direction
90 but we want the up arrow to go up and
so we actually want to click on this
circle to the up arrow and in in Tynker
up is zero degrees which again scratch
is different but I'm sure that it
doesn't really matter that much and then
the next thing we want to do is we want
to go to the top command and grab a move
10 pixels great and one thing that I
like to do when I code it's got a fancy
name it's called iterative enhancements
I like to test it whenever I can so
right now if I start my game and I hit
the up arrow
LarryBoy should go up now one thing did
happen that might have been surprising
to you is my LarryBoy actually turned
right so I hit play and then I hit up
arrow and my LarryBoy turned well I
actually didn't want him to turn so I
want to fix that so we wrote just a
little bit of code and it's already got
a bug here's how we're gonna fix it
we're gonna set his rotation style to
where the image doesn't rotate if that
makes sense the way we do that is to go
to events we grab an on start so we
almost always have some kind of on
start and then we want to go looking for
a very like obscure command
it's called set rotation style and we
want to set his rotation style to
doesn't rotate there's multiple ways we
can do this but I like to do it via code
so go to motion and let's go looking for
this odd command right here set rotation
style and we can set the rotation style
to all around which is the default which
is what he is now left right which our
monster did that on like the very first
day or don't rotate and I actually want
him the image I want the image to don't
rotate so if I run it again now and I
hit up arrow you can see that he kind of
goes up and he doesn't rotate and that's
going to work out better now if you try
to go left and
right he's not gonna do that if you're
trying to come back down he's not gonna
do that either right and so we need to
add those other things I find the
easiest way to add it is to click on up
arrow do a ctrl C a control V and that
will copy it and paste it and then you
have to do all four directions right so
maybe I'll do left arrow and I want the
left arrow to make me point in the left
direction so negative 90 in this case so
see if you can do the next two without
me it should be a pretty clear pattern
so go ahead and pause the video and see
if you can get all the different
directions worked all right so if you
paused it and tried it you should come
up with commands that look like this
so you should have up down right and
left and then of course you want to try
it to make sure it works there could be
all kinds of little things that are
wrong but you should have up go up down
go down right goes right and left goes
left and in addition to moving he's also
like pointing in that direction but the
image isn't rotating that and that works
out good later right by the way just to
kind of mention some little mistakes
that you can make maybe you clicked off
and it's 175 or something like that
that's okay it's not the end of the
world you can't actually just type in
this box though it's just a giant pain
because it tries to like autocomplete um
so do the best you can with it but I'm
trying to make sure that they do end up
at these different degrees I had trouble
typing in it there but make sure you've
got motion ready to go all right so now
we've got our hero's ability to move I
think what I'd like to do next is go
tackle the drawing the drawing step so
in order to do some drawing we're going
to have to create a background on our
stage so our stage has no backgrounds or
anything so click on the gear icon for
the stage so this little gear that's
right over here for the background
what we want to do I'm sorry for the
stage what we want to do is add a background
so go and click on add background and
then we want to draw a background from
scratch so we're not using using
anything at all so click on the little
art paintbrush up here or draw an image and
then you have to click again on draw an
image I always think that's silly that
you draw twice all right so now we're
gonna do some drawing now what I'm gonna
be careful of to begin with is I'm gonna
be careful to make sure that my zoom
level is such that I can see the whole
board because the first thing I want to
do is I want to put a ring around the
outside and if I've accidentally zoomed
in because I do this all the time and I
draw a ring here on the outside it's not
really around the outside right now what
I want to do is I want to pick what
color my maze is gonna be sometimes it
can be thematic to your characters but
it also it can be nice if you pick a
color that isn't likely to appear in
your characters that's not a big deal
but pick a color that you think would be
fun so mine are kind of VeggieTales I
think that VeggieTales I think of green
when I think of VeggieTales so I'm gonna
pick kind of like a greenish color for
my maze today hopefully that's not the
exact same shade of green as something
in LarryBoy but I'll risk it now
what I want to do first is I want to
draw a rectangle around the whole
perimeter so to draw rectangles it's
actually a shape which is under the line
tool and what I want to do is I want a
hollow rectangle now this hollow
rectangle has a transparent middle and
then a border around the outside I'm
gonna make the size of mine be 10 just
so it's a slightly bigger border and I'm
gonna make the opacity be 100% it's kind
of nice to make your walls a little
thicker so I think a nice 10 pixel wall would look nice
other than just like a really thin wall now
what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna draw it
to where it's pretty close to as big as
it can get
now if you do a perfect job then that's
great but I don't want you to worry
about doing a perfect job because what
happens is this once you draw it you
have a little bit of a chance to move it
around until you let go of it so if
you make it so I did perfect on the top
and the right and the bottom but my left
needs to be adjusted over here now if
you did not even close to perfect right
that's fine too so I'm just gonna do
mine again so let's say that I did this
right so it wasn't even close to perfect
I could just move everyone out to get it
perfect now if you made it really really
small then this is gonna make it look a
little stretchy but as long as you're
close it should work out fine so that is
my wall that's gonna make sure that
everybody stays in bounds you can't just
like go outside the maze and do stuff
the next thing I'm going to do is I'm
going to switch to use the line tool now
for the line tool I'm gonna continue to
use the same color I'm going to continue
to use ten pixels in full opacity and
I'm gonna draw my maze now here's where
the creative part comes in you have to
draw a maze to where your hero has to
like get through the maze and get to the
target and it has to be possible right
so you have to think about how big your
sprite is and there has to be a path by
which they can get through it doesn't have
to be like a hard maze to solve but it
should be something that like provides
obstacles so that your villain can make
it hard right so what I'm going to do is
I always kind of like to start with a
little straight period up on the side
but you can do whatever you want and I'm
thinking about you know my hero and I
predict that he can probably get up this
shoot fine and then he can probably get
across the top there now after the
initial line you know I'm gonna maybe
make him go back down you can do
whatever you want so go ahead and take a
minute and draw your your maze right so
I'm just gonna kind of draw a pretty
simple maze and think about where your
your targets gonna be and you know think
about the fact that they have to get to
the target so I think I'm gonna put Bob
he's my target somewhere like inside of
here
right
and then after you draw a little bit
what you'll have to do is you'll have to
go check it like with your character and
see like where are they where they can
get through and where you've made a an
accidentally impossible game right so I
don't know maybe I'll try that one
and if you don't like something you put
in just do an undo on it
and just try again right and then once
you so I I may be done I don't really
know if I'm done or not I'm gonna go
back and I'm just gonna walk LarryBoy
around and I'm gonna see if I'm done
right so I'm just gonna kind of see yep
that seems kind of good yep I made it
through there ooh that was kind of
close that means that probably something
later is in trouble now if I do touch the
walls nothing bad is gonna happen to me
right now
right I'm just gonna go right through
them but this is where I kind of like
test my game and I see like this area is
probably too easy right so I'm probably
gonna make that a little harder and then
come around here and then that's
gonna be close so I make it try to make
sure you make it by more than just like
one pixel because our games gonna need a
little bit of freedom so I think that
mine actually wasn't too bad I think the
thing that I'm gonna do is I'm going to
edit it some more so I'm gonna click on
the pencil now and I'm gonna make one
spot harder right and so I'm gonna make
this spot right here harder all right so
I'm gonna walk around and help my
campers out a little bit but no reason
for you to see that so play around until
you're pretty happy with your maze and I
think that that mine looks looks pretty
good here alright so half an hour later
my teams got their mazes drawn just
just teasing
but Keegan's got an elaborate plan to
add things to his maze bow and Bowen you mind if
we see your maze it looks good good looking maze
Bowen and then of course McKinley
McKinley do you have a maze oh she's got an
elaborate maze so depending on on who
you are you might want to make it kind of simple
or kind of complex or Keegan's got a
plan to add crazy stuff later but make
sure you've got a maze that you're happy
with the next thing we're going to do is
we're going to actually add some code
for our villain next so we're gonna kind
of do this in a weird order today so
what we want to do is if we want to add
code for our villain we have to select
our villain from the list so my villain
is moetato - and what moetato is gonna do
is he's gonna glide around the screen in
different places to make it harder for
LarryBoy to get to the target now this
does require a little bit of planning
right so you have to think about where
should he glide to kind of make a fun
game so obviously one of the places I'm
gonna glide is I'm gonna glide like into
this area and then back out and then
maybe I'll glide somewhere through the
bottom but it's kind of nice to come up
with a pattern you think will be kind of
fun so maybe I'll go over and back and
then maybe I'll go down and it doesn't
it doesn't really matter but if you have
some goal for where do you want your
villain to go that can actually
be be better and we're gonna need a
sheet of paper for this so I'm gonna
have to pause it and go get a sheet of
paper because I forgot to get a sheet of
paper and we're gonna pick some
different places that we want our
villain to go to and we're gonna write
down those positions so I'm gonna go get
my sheet of paper you should too alright
welcome back I got my paper so what
we're gonna do is I'm gonna write down
different positions for my villain so
I'm gonna get him where I want him
so right now I've kind of got him in the
middle by the way if you want your stage
bigger you can just click on the stage
tab and it'll make it bigger for you so
his first position here I kind of looked
down in the corner I can't move them
house though I just have to look it's
negative thirty-two and ninety and maybe
that's what he'll start first and so I'm
gonna take my pencil a number write down
negative looks like it moved to negative 28 91 so
I've written that down next I have to
pick a new spot for him so maybe I'll
move him over here next and I'll write
that number down so I'll just say that's
negative five five zero 52 again I'm
looking in that lower right corner I
can't move my mouse there because then
it'll change the
position so go around and get a few
positions where you want your villain to
glide to and he's gonna smoothly glide
between them so I've got mine I actually
just just did it already and I've got a
list here all right so let's go back to
our code so our code make sure you're
selecting your villain it's like this
it's gonna have an on start which we've
done a couple times so I did that kind
of quickly it's the first thing in the
first category we're going to do
something forever so I go into control I
find a forever loop and then what we're
gonna do is for each position we're
gonna bring over a glide to - so here's a
glide right here and what I like to do
is I like to put in the number of
commands that are necessary first so it
looks like I've got seven commands so
you can you know maybe you wrote down three
maybe you wrote down like thirty
probably I wouldn't do more than seven
seven is quite a few and now I'm just
gonna start typing in my numbers right
in general I like the glide to happen
over three seconds that's kind of a
smoother glide and what I do to hop
between them
is I hit tab you don't have to hit tab you
can click into each one that's fine tab
makes it go a little faster right and so
this is a good game for parents and kids
to do together so your write down all
your numbers and then you have the
parent hold the list and they just say
you know where am I supposed to go to
next and so you just tell them so I
think I've got mine almost done oops I tried
to do one a little too fast there so a
three there 571 maybe I'll speed up the
video to where you don't have to watch
me type every single number but I'm
almost there all right five two five so
pause the video and go at your speed you don't
have to go at my speed on things and
make sure you've got all your positions
right and then when you hit play
something kind of neat should happen is
your villain should glide around to
different positions now here's where
game design is important you
have to make sure that your game is
playable and fun right
so for example with mine Larry might be
going a little too slow right by the way
I can still go through walls but we're
gonna fix that with our code but you
have to make sure that it's possible to
not only get through your maze but
possible to do it without hitting your
villain and the idea through your game
is ah with good strategy you could avoid
where your villain gets to so I think
it's wise to memorize where your villain
goes but you can actually like make sure
your game is playable so mine is gonna
be hard but I think
it's doable so I'm gonna give it a go
for now so I'm gonna call it good enough
the next thing I want to do just because
I was thinking about it is I want to
play with letting you change the speed
of your hero so right now the speed of
our hero is that every time there's a
press he moves 10 pixels now here's what
happens in coding all the time this is a
good lesson let's say I wanted him to go
faster
well I change this one to 15 well I've
got to change them all to 15 right so
I've got in my code you can just watch
for now I've got in my code the number
for his speed in four different places I
say oh I want to go faster than that I
want to actually go at 20 and if you
have this problem a lot where you've got
the same number in your code at multiple
places and you want them to all match it's
silly to have to change them in all four
places every time so we're gonna make a
variable this is a coding concept that
people use a lot it's called avoiding
magic numbers so I've got this magic
number in my code in four places
whenever that happens it's a good time
to make a variable so go to variables
and then click on create variable and I
like to call this variable speed and
speed is for only this actor now this
variable is different than we've ever
used variables before so this is going to avoid having a magic
number in many places it's not going to
change right so it's not ever going to
change we're going to set it once so I'm
gonna grab a set I'm gonna set the speed
once
and I'm just going to go and let you
look at what I did here I did that
little fast I'm gonna set it once and
then I'm gonna use it in multiple
different spots so I created this variable 15
and then I'm going to use it at all four
of these spots so instead of having this
magic number in four places I drop in
the variable speed into everywhere I use
it so this appears to be the exact same
code but it's better because now I can
change the speed in one place and it
changes it everywhere it's pretty simple
to see the four places here but in code
it happens all the time where you do
things like this and so now I've got my
code to where it's easy to maintain
it doesn't repeat myself so that's dry
don't repeat yourself and I've avoided
the magic number of 20 appearing in
multiple places inside my code and you
can also play with your speed until you
think that your game is good and
possible oh I've got a vicious spot
there in my game oh I'll have to figure
that out I think 20 is fine for me but
you can go at whatever speed you would
like to go all right
good time to click on save right so
we've done done a lot of things now what
I want to do is I want to make Larry no
longer be able to pass through walls
adding this is going to make my game a
little harder to test but it's going to
be important to make Larry not pass
through walls so click on your hero this
is something we have to always check
we're gonna check am i touching a wall
am i touching a wall am i touching a
wall so that is a if statement that is
for inside of a forever loop so go to
control find a forever loop stick it on
to Larry's in his on start thread/block of code and
then he does a couple things forever but
one of them is he always checks am i
touching a wall now touching a wall is a
color so am i touching this color
now it's a good thing you got your
pencil and paper because we're about to
have to use it again right so we want to
know what color is my maze so I've got
to go back in and edit my maze I'm not
going to really edit it so that I can
figure out what color that green is so
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
click on the pencil for my stage and so
that pencil is going to take me into
edit mode for the stage and then I want
to figure out exactly what shade of
green did I use so this process we use
before but it takes a while to get it
down you click on the eyedropper you
click on the color then you click on the
color chooser and you want the hex value
I am sure that Tynker will make this
process better some day I'm 100%
convinced of it but today this is the
best way to get the color that I happen
to know of again colors will be numbers
and letters a through f and it can be hard to
tell the difference between like an O (letter)
and a zero but it's actually not hard
because you know it's a zero it can also
be hard to tell the difference between
like an eight and a B and now that one
is hard but get your number write it
down and then you can go back to your
code so you have to kind of like exit
the stage here and what I want to put in
here is I want to say if touching color
then do stuff touching color is a
sensing so you know it's gonna be in
sensing and I want touching color
it looks like it's the fourth one down click in
this box and type typing in this box can
be a little annoying
if you get it this is just like we did with with
other things if you get it you'll get a
confirmation that it worked because the
the background will change to that color
and so I can see that I have a match
between my maze green and my touching
color green here all right so once
you've got once you fought with it
enough to make that work I'd help my
campers out a little bit we're ready to
do stuff inside of this code so now he's
going to know hey I am touching this
color now I want something to happen so
the thing that I want to happen is I
want him to bounce off right so this is
where a little theatrics is good but
like if you walk and then you hit a wall
when you hit a wall you do a couple
things you turn around and then you take
a step backwards right and so that's
what we're going to do so the first
thing we're going to do when we hit a
wall is turn around so you turn around
we'll see how good people are with their
angles so we're gonna turn some number
of degrees to turn around
Keegan do you have any idea how many
degrees do I need to turn to turn
completely around I need to turn
180 that's right so I need to turn 180
degrees and then I need to step away
from the wall the right number of pixels
so I'm going to use a move and now we
need to move away that magic number
again so that we kind of like bounce
back and so we need to move speed pixels
away right
maybe instead of speed I should have
called it like distance but that's okay so
I need to drop in to that instead of
move 10 pixels I need to move speed
pixels so I got to go to variables and I
got to take that speed and I've got to
drop it in now I could run it right now
and that would be a fine test but it's
gonna happen too fast because in
Tynker if you touch the wall it's gonna
instantly move you back to where you
came from and it's gonna be so fast that
you're not gonna see it so we're gonna
put in a really short time delay just so
the user can see yeah I just hit a wall
right so we're gonna put in a really
short time delay so go to control and
the very bottom command nope it's not
the very bottom it's close to the bottom
is wait one seconds and what we're going
to do is we're going to wait just a very
small amount so I'm gonna wait point
zero five seconds and the reason I'm
doing that is because you have hit the
wall and I want the user to kind of
like see themselves inside the wall and
then I'm gonna move them back
now it doesn't matter whether it's at
the very top or whether it's after the
180 those don't matter but it does need
to be before the move 10 pixels all
right so we've got enough code that we
can try it
so Larry should always be checking to
see if he's hitting the wall if he is
hitting the wall he waits just a second
and then he backs it up so right now I
can give it a go so now whenever Larry
hits a wall he kind of bounces right now
if you want to try this during that half
second pause it is possible to keep
moving forwards so if you like really
go nuts you might be able to plow
through a wall yeah but that's a feature
that we just kind of hide from our users
so there are ways we can fix it but I'm
not worried about it but when you hit
the wall you bounce off but know that
as the creator of your game you can
plow through a wall if you do it hard
enough right you just have to hit the
button faster than point zero five
seconds all right going good I'm gonna
click on save just because I'm happy
about things now the next thing I want
to do is I want to lose the game if I
hit Moetato and I want to win the
game if I make it to Bob right so that's
my goal next so I need to always check
if those things are happening so I need
two more if statements so what I'm gonna
do is I'm still in LarryBoy I'm still in
my hero I'm gonna add two if statements
into my loop so total I'm checking for
three things am i touching a wall and if
so I want to bounce um am i touching
moetato because if so I lose and am i
touching Larry because if I if I am then
I win sorry am i touching Bob got the
wrong word there now this if statement
so if this condition then is not a color
we're actually looking for a sprite so
go into sensing now in the past we've
used touching color but that's not what
we're going to do this time we're going
to use this is crazy we're gonna use
touching mouse pointer and you're like
well that's weird why are you saying
touching Mouse
pointer and it's because you can change
mouse pointer to be someone else so you
have to decide which order you want to
do things maybe I'll do my villain first
so this is my lose first and then I'll
do touching Bob that's my win so do
yours in the same order of mine and that
way to be less confusing so do whatever
makes you lose first and then whatever
makes you win second so think about you
know your names of your actors over here
and lose first win second so if you lose
you've got to decide what do you what do
you want to happen you could make the
whole game end that would be fine or you
could just say something and move them back
to the start I think what I'm gonna do
and again this is a design choice that
you want is I'm just gonna move them
back to the start and then say something
that's like you lose try again or
something like that right alright so now
what I need to do is I need to know
where Larry is at the start right so he
is at a certain X&Y
so you need your pencil and your paper
again so move your hero to where they
start at and look to see what that
position is so for me it is negative 5 9
0 negative 2 7 9 hey that's almost my
phone number just teasing the next thing
you want to do is you want to go to
motion and you want to find a go to X Y
now it starts off with an X of 0 and a y
of 0 and you want to change that to your original starting numbers
from before like that and so now if I touch moetato it will
take me back to where I start the game if you
would like you could also have this
command at the start of your code this
is completely optional but if you click
on this handle you do a ctrl-c ctrl-v
you could if you wanted move this to
also be at the start of your code and
the only value for that is that if
somehow you kind of like mess up where
larry is at like during your development
even if I say to start him up here he's
gonna actually like go there when my
game starts so if you want you can have
that at the top not required but it
definitely needs to be here so what I'm
going to do is if I touch moetato I'm going
to zoom to that spot and then I'm gonna
say something saying something is in
looks right because we're gonna have a
speech bubble that pops up so I'm gonna
go to looks and I'm going to look for
the giant speech bubble here's a giant
speech bubble oops and I want to put it
right after the go to X Y and I'm gonna
say you lose play again and you can
choose to say this however you want to
say it if you want it to appear as
though Larry is saying it you could use
a rectangular speech bubble you could
use a top message a bottom message a
centered message it doesn't matter just
because it's something I haven't ever
tried before I'm gonna say a message
right in the center of the screen and
I'm gonna make it huge 48 it's pretty
huge alright maybe 36 is plenty now this
is going to be pretty easy to test we
just need to run into our villain and if
we run into our villain it's just gonna
warp us back to here and then it's gonna
say you lose play again so go ahead and
try it
so get your hero to where you think
they're going to be in trouble and then
whenever it hits it mine set in giant
letters you lose play again cool so I
can try that one more time
maybe I'll make it bigger so I've got to
wait for my villain to finish his loop
so that he can get back over here I've
got to memorize how my villain moves so
I can actually win my game but when he
hits him it says you lose play again I'm
pretty happy with that so the nice thing
is
oops
I did something silly I almost exited my
whole game so the nice thing is is that
we're almost there right so if we hit
moetato we lose and we're going to let
people keep playing and so now the only
thing we need to do is what do we want
to have happen if we want to hit Bob so
hitting Bob so one thing we want to do
is we want to say you win right so if
you win we want to go to looks find a
giant text bubble and we want to say you
win and again you could have it look
like Larry saying it you could have it
show up on the screen whatever you want
to do just for giggles I'm gonna have it
look like Larry saying it you could also
do things like change the background
color the font color whatever you want
to do to try your game now once we hit
Larry and it says you win we've got to
decide what we want to happen in that
case as well so one of the enhancements
I'm gonna encourage you to make is to
make a different like maze I'm not going
to show that but I'm gonna have you like
move to some spot and then like show the
next maze right but for now we just need
to decide what we want to do so you can
do whatever you'd like
maybe maybe what you want to do is you
just want to go back to the start after
they finish talking and then they could
just play again if they wanted for now
so I think that that is is good enough
for me there is no right answer this is
your game there is no single right
answer but I do want to test it and see
if it works now one way to test it is to
actually like get to that spot there's
nothing wrong with that but sometimes
the best way to test your game is to
cheat and to figure up how
how to cheat to make testing easier
right so I want to test this without
going to a lot of work so it would be
really easy to win if Larry started
right there right so here's what I'm
gonna do to cheat is I'm gonna write
down my cheater spot so my cheater spot is 280 189 so my
code may or may not work I don't even
know yet I haven't tested it and in
order to test it I'm gonna cheat so I've
got my cheater spot and here's what I'm
gonna do I'm gonna add some code that I
know I'm gonna take out later and I'm
going to add my cheater code just before
my forever loop I'm gonna go to my
cheater spot cheating is good for
testing right so now this this line
of code I'm gonna have to remember to
take it out before I ship/publish my game
because it's just for a test but now
when I hit play Larry goes immediately
to my cheater spot and I step over and I
say you win so that is how you develop a
game by cheating right it looked like it
worked perfectly to me I just step right
over and hit Larry and I won so now I'm
ready to delete my cheater code to
delete just that line you grab the right
handle and you drag it out of the game
so there I just drug it out so now I
think my game is is ready to go so now
I'm gonna give it one full test so it
might take me a little while to win my
game so moetato goes over and so I use
this opportunity to kind of like get
around and then moetato goes down and
that way now I happen to know that
moetato is gonna spend a lot of time over
there so I'm gonna just hang out right
here for a second
until moetato has passed me now I'm
gonna make my run for it Bob oh all
right
so try your game out as well see if
yours is playable and winnable but I
think that I have mine to where I can
win so it says you win and it snaps me
back to there
great so for me mine is done I might
have to give my campers just a minute to
finish theirs but I'm gonna go ahead and
hit save and publish and I'm also going
to tell you so I'm gonna get my campers
a minute to finish theirs then I'll help
them out I'm also going to tell you what
I think some fun enhancements are to
this game so one enhancement that I
think is fun is to make a second
background like a second maze right and
the way you can do that I'll just kind
of say enough to get you started is you
go into the costumes you say add
background you make a new background
right so maybe I have a new background
like this and then when you win you go
back to here I'm doing this fast because
this is an optional thing right you
could actually switch to the next
background and so now just to show it
faster I'm going to put back in my
cheater cheater code and so now when I
when you win it'll say you win and then
it'll start you on the next level right
oh this level was really hard no way I'm
getting through there actually that
color is not my maze color so I can just
walk right through it hey yay and then
if I win this level it says you win and
then it takes me to the next level
and so you can make as many different
levels as you would like but to make it
fun you do have to use that same maze
color
so that's just one enhancement that you
can make if you wanted to make your game
better another thing you could do to
make your game better is you could add
sounds people love sounds but when you
win you could play a sound when you hit
a wall you could play a sound just to
kind of show how to add one sound
maybe I'll go into LarryBoy I'm gonna
click on LarryBoy's gear go to sounds
and say add sounds and maybe there's
like a blink or something like that like
a boing yeah there's a Boing and so for
Larry maybe if he touches the wall I'll
make him go boing right and so I'm gonna
go sound play sound until done
maybe I'll play it right there so any
time Larry hits a wall he's got to go
boing right and so just kind of an
added little feature so I am
intentionally not showing you everything
you could do because that's kind of what
makes the game fun right oh I just realized
I should play the boing after I move
him back right because I have play
boing until done another thing you can
do by the way is play until done pauses
everything you could also just play it
without waiting for it to finish alright
so I think that the mine is ready to go
I'm curious to see how my campers fared
today campers are you ready for me to
see how you guys did today kind of
that's what we got today I'm sure that
we can fix it as we go so Keegan how's
the the minion project coming along so
you made your speed very fast and being
very fast you've got a couple a couple
minor bugs so by being so fast you can
kind of walk through some of your walls
I'll tell you what oh and you're just
holding down the movement oh so
you're like blitzing through things
looks great buddy did you have fun
building that do you have ideas for
enhancements you might make Bowen
you're up next
Bowen you ready to show the world
your game so Bowen has a gecko from PJ
Masks so hopefully some of you recognize
the the PJ Masks reference so gecko has
to try to get through his maze nice one
gecko and he's trying to get over to the
little gecko whoa you went the low route
was that a is that a design choice there Bowen
you got the makings of a web designer or
a game designer you win hey Bowen was
that pretty awesome yeah did you have
fun today are you able to speak
[Laughter]
all right let's check out McKinley's alright
McKinley what have you got so you've got
the horse and the horse is getting
through her elaborate maze McKinley made
fun of me because my maze was so easy
hey you walked right through the wall
cheaters cheaters never win so if you do
have a problem with lots of cheaters in
your game take out that that delay of
point zero five seconds and that's gonna
stop a bunch of cheating so you can you
can decide you're the game designer you
can decide how you feel about cheating
but if you wanted to prevent some of
that walking through walls nonsense take
that command out and they won't get the
feedback why they can't go through the
walls they'll just hit the wall and it
just like they just won't be able to
move but that will prevent the cheating
that happens right maybe a sound effect
is better than a visual right all right
so we hope you enjoyed today I know I
had a lot of fun add some crazy
enhancements do make sure to share
yours with the community that way I can
see it and other people in the class can
see it and it makes it fun all right
we'll see you next time that's it bye
[Music]